<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sundry considerations touching naturalization of aliens whereby the alledged advantages thereby are confuted, and the contrary mischiefs thereof are detected and discovered.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833632</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833632</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38110</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61979)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38110)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2178:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sundry considerations touching naturalization of aliens whereby the alledged advantages thereby are confuted, and the contrary mischiefs thereof are detected and discovered.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naturalization --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Naturalization --  England --  Economic aspects. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Aliens --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38110:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>SUNDRY CONSIDERATIONS TOUCHING Naturalization of Aliens: WHEREBY The alledged Advantages thereby are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, and the contrary Miſchiefs thereof are detected and diſcovered.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THERE being much Diſcourſe about Naturalizing Foreigners, and great Conveniences and Inconveniences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuggeſted</hi> pro &amp; con, <hi>as to the Conſequences thereof in reſpect to Trade, I beg leave, having my ſelf an Intereſt in the Trade of this Nation, that I may deliver the Senſe of a worthy Patriot,</hi> (<hi>Sir</hi> Matthew Hales <hi>late Lord Chief Juſtice of</hi> England) <hi>who in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38110:2"/>a Manuſcript, accidentally falling into my hands, affirms, and from the following Arguments proves, the Naturalization of Foreigners never to have been the judgment of honeſt, thinking, but only the opinion of unthinking, notional, or deſigning Men, and the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences that follow hereupon never to he remedied. It is a Subject that very nearly concerns the Good of this Kingdom, the</hi> Engliſh <hi>having been always tenacious of their Liberty, and Jealous of being wrong'd in their Trade by Foreigners, as is apparent by the many commotions formerly on that account, eſpecially the</hi> Ill May-Day <hi>in the</hi> 9th. <hi>Year of King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth</hi> (1657.) <hi>of which our Hiſtorians take eſpecial notice: If it was thus, when Trade was in its Infancy, it may poſſibly be much more ſo, now the Trade of</hi> Europe <hi>is chiefly in our hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And at this preſent time the countenancing of a Foreign Trade, (tho' in a Siſter Nation) to the prejudice of our own Merchants ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be of ſuch high and National concern, that both Houſes of Parliament (thoſe great Aſſertors of our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Liberties</hi>) <hi>have taken notice of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to wave further prefacing, I come directly to the ſubject Matter, and obſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. THAT there is no preſent neceſſity of any ſuch thing: not from abroad, for we are not under the fear or power of Foreign Princes that might impoſe it upon us. Nor from within, for tho' we have many Foreigners among us, yet they are not able ſo far to give us the Law, as by a bold im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to command it: The Natives of this Kingdom very much exceed them in ſtrength and number, neither do the Natives of this Kingdom, except ſome few ſpeculative and notional men, deſire, much leſs demand it; ſo that we who have above five hundred years con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued under diſtinct Policy from other Nations, and have enjoyed the Priviledge of our own Kingdom, without communication thereof promiſcuouſly and generally to Aliens may continue ſo ſtill without the neceſſity of Naturalization of Aliens; and for ought I know, with as much happineſs, and wealth, and honour, as our Anceſtors have done
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38110:2"/>before us. And altho' it is true, that while the King, of <hi>England</hi> had their Hereditary Territories in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> of thoſe Territories were in effect by the Union Naturalized as <hi>Poſtnati</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> are with us at this day, yet that is nothing to the buſineſs in hand, namely an univerſal Naturalization; ſo that there ſeems nothing of neceſſity in the caſe, only if there be any thing of reaſon for it, it muſt be the buſineſs of convenience, and that in relation to Trade.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Therefore the conveniences of Naturalization of Aliens muſt be conſidered, and this certainly muſt be in relation to Trade: And herein will be theſe Conſiderations following. Namely; Firſt, What kind of Naturalization that muſt be which muſt moſt advance Trade. Secondly, What kind of advance of Trade will ariſe by ſuch Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalization.</p>
            <p>Touching the former of theſe; certainly the general reaſon of the advance of Trade by Naturalizing Aliens muſt be, becauſe it will be a means to invite Foreigners to come hither, to bring their Stocks, their Wealth, their Trading, their Manufactures hither, where they may find as great, if not greater advantage, than they have in other, or their own, Countries.</p>
            <p>The conſequence whereof muſt needs be, that the more ample and extenſive their Priviledge is, the greater the advance of Trade will thereby be; becauſe the Invitation is the greater, and on the other ſide the more narrow, contracted, and reſtrictive, the Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation is, the leſs it will conduce to the advance of Trade.</p>
            <p>The Naturalization therefore muſt be Univerſal. Firſt, In reſpect of extent, it muſt extend to all Perſons of all Nations, of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Proteſtants, Papiſts. Jews, Mahometans, Turks, Moors, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, for otherwiſe it anſwers not the Latitude of the Deſign, if Trade be the Saint that is adored only, other Conſiderations muſt be laid aſide, or elſe the Latitude of the Deſign is narrowed. Secondly, In reſpect of Intention or the Nature of the Priviledge, it muſt be to all Intents and Purpoſes, there muſt be no diſcrimination in Cuſtoms nor in Hereditary Succeſſions, nor in any other Priviledges belonging to natural born Subjects.</p>
            <p>Touching the later, the advance of Trade hereby will be thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> is moſt certainly in the moſt advanſageous place of the World, to be the Miſtreſs of Trade, both in reference to <hi>Europe, Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> the <hi>Eaſtern, Weſtern, Northern,</hi> and <hi>Southern</hi> World,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38110:3"/>it hath the beſt Ports and Harbours for Shipping of any place in the World, and not only the beſt, but the moſt numerous, as well as moſt uſeful. It hath the moſt advantageous Rivers, for the tranſporting into the Body of the Kingdom, and educing out of it all manner of Commodities, as <hi>Thames, Severn, Humber, Tyne,</hi> and by divers others, and by new Cuts and Sluices there might without much difficulty in compariſon of the Profit, for the communication between the Ports themſelves, and the Ports and Inland Towns. Again, it hath Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for Shipping, is not far diſtant from the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, for its ſupply of Maſts and Cordage, hath Iron. Tin, Lead, Leather, Wooll, Cloth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the maintenance of Trade, is excellently fitted with fiſhing for the increaſe of Marriners, hath all ſorts of Victuals for the Victualling of Ships, and in Sum is ſupplied with all conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and accommodations to make it the common Port almoſt of the whole World. And beſides all this, though it be very populous for a Continent, it is nothing in compariſon of what it might be as an Iſland or Common Port; there is room enough for the reception of Millions of People in thoſe vaſt unpeopled Plains and Coaſts almoſt in all Countries; the <hi>Netherlands</hi> that are not much larger than <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> yet in reſpect of their Trade are infinitely more populous than the moſt populous part of <hi>England,</hi> except <hi>London, Briſtol, Exeter</hi> and <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and ſome other Port-Towns.</p>
            <p>And therefore were the Country free for all Nations to come into, with the ſame advantage as in their own, certainly all theſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, beſides the pleaſantneſs and temperateneſs of the Country would invite infinite numbers of Foreigners, eſpecially the Trading and Manufacturing part of them to come and ſettle here; and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences hereof to the Trade and Wealth of the Kingdom would be ſuch as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. It would preſently advance the Price and Rents of Land by the increaſe of the Wealth, the Trade, and the Inhabitants of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. It would draw over the Trading Merchants and their Stocks hither, which would in a moment advance the Wealth of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. It would bring over the Artificers of all Foreign Countries hither, and the rather conſidering that here would be the great Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine of Commerce, and alſo a ſufficient ſtore of Materials for their Employment, which either are here native, or would be ſpeedily acquired, as Iron, Steel, Tin, Lead, Wooll, Hemp, Flax.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38110:3"/>
4thly. And by this means the Natives of this Kingdom would be inſtructed in all kind of Manufactures, and which is yet a greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage the idle Poor of this Kingdom which is at preſent the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and will be in time the deſtruction of the Kingdom, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Wealth of the Kingdom being habituated, and as it were fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the induſtry of Foreigners, who at this time, and almoſt in all ages have been more happy in Manufacture than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> who have moſt of their curious Manufactures from the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5thly. And by this means <hi>England</hi> will be the <hi>commune &amp; nobile Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porium</hi> of the World, their Shipping, Marriners and Trade, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently their Wealth, Power, and Strength immenſly increaſed, for experience and reaſon tell us, that whatſoever place is the Seat of Trade, that place muſt abound with Wealth, Shipping and Marriners, as is ſeen at this day, eſpecially in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Venice,</hi> for by theſe means the Merchandize of all parts of the World, will in effect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Native Commodities of this Kingdom, the ſame being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the common Receptacle and Store-Houſe thereof for Exportation into all Places of the World.</p>
            <p>And theſe be many of the moſt conſiderable Reaſons that ſeem to evince the convenience of this Expedient, and indeed carry a ſpecious Pretext for it.</p>
            <p>But for all this I do think that neither the event will anſwer the expectation, and if it did yet the inconveniences that accompany this thing will be too great.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, Therefore this Expedient ſeems utterly incompetent for the Ends propounded, namely, the Increaſe of the Wealth and Trade of this Kingdom, and for the Evidence thereof, I ſhall not uſe Notions and Suppoſitions, but appeal to experience and obſervation, which in a matter of this nature proves more effectually than conjectural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Imaginations, and I ſhall uſe but theſe two Inſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, If this were a means to increaſe the Trade, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Wealth of this Kingdom, it would have been the means there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in ſome former Ages, and if it had been ſo, ſurely they had had as much reaſon, both in reſpect of their Wiſdom, and Prudence, and Intereſt, to have ſeen it and allowed it in former Times; but in all the Tracts of former Times, this was never ſo eſteemed or found, and therefore we have as much reaſon to believe that it would not ſo prove now.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:38110:4"/>
And that former Times never eſteemed or found this Expedient uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the increaſe of the Wealth and Trade of this Nation, is evident in this, that they ever moſt ſtrictly kept up the diſcriminations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Natives and Aliens. Firſt, The Excluſion of them from the priviledge of purchaſing Lands in <hi>England,</hi> hath always made their Purchaſes forfeit to the Crown, and their Iſſue diſabled from Hereditary Succeſſion, which in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended alſo to the purchaſng of Houſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The Aliens always even from the firſt Settlement of the great Cuſtoms in <hi>Edward</hi> the I. his time, as in all Acts of Parliament for Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies ſince, have been charged with an increaſe of Cuſtoms above the Native.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Great care was ever uſed in Naturalizations by Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, which were rarely granted and upon ſpecial Reaſons.</p>
            <p>It is true, that in all times ſome particular encouragement were given to Foreigners to bring in their Arts here, as to the Weavers in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the II. and alſo to Merchants to bring in their Goods and ſell them here, as by the Statute of the 9th. of <hi>Edward</hi> the III. for ſelling by retail in <hi>London,</hi> and other Cities, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to the <hi>Hanſe</hi> Merchants, and the Merchants of the <hi>Stile Yard</hi> by King <hi>Henry</hi> the III. by King <hi>Edward</hi> the I. in his <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> by King <hi>Edward</hi> the IV. in enlarging the Priviledges of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the <hi>Stile-Yard,</hi> but ſtill they maintained and kept up the Diſcrimination between <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Foreigners, as to the point of Naturalization and diſparity of Cuſtoms in general.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, In all Ages Merchants in amity had, and to this day have as great liberty in point of Trade and Commerce in this Kingdom, except as to the Purchaſing of Lands, and equality of Cuſtoms, as the univerſal Naturalization of them would give, our Ports are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly open to them (except the late Act for encouraging Navigation) as they would be if Naturalized, and the convenience of our Ports are as much now as they would be then. So that if the point of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and convenience of our Ports are as much now as they would be then, it is not credible that the giving them priviledge of purchaſing Lands, which is collateral to Trade, and the little diſproportion of their Cuſtoms would ſo abundantly increaſe the Trade of the Kingdom as to matter of Commerce, the ſuppoſed grand advantage, over what it now doth.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38110:4"/>
2dly, But touching the ſecond conſiderable, I ſay, that altho' ſome poſſible advantage might grow to our Trade by ſuch an extenſive Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, yet the inconveniences that would thereby ariſe to the Safety, Satisfaction, Preſervation and Wealth of this Kingdom, would exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively ſurmount that imaginary advantage, as will evidently appear by theſe enſuing Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. It would in a little time ſurcharge the Kingdom with Aliens, and either drive out, ſtreighten, conſume, or quite blot out the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation. If the Wealth they bring with them were ſmall and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, they would be our Burthen, if great, they would be our Canker to eat the Natives out of their Poſſeſſions, and by degrees, transfer our Poſſeſſions to Strangers; and ſo while by Naturalizing them, we ſhould demonſtrate a great Zeal to the increaſe of Trade, we ſhould at the ſame time diſcover a great neglect, and indeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying of our Country and Countrymen, exterminating them, that we might increaſe Trade for Strangers.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, It would preſently give an univerſal diſguſt to the whole Kingdom, who would reaſonably think that we ſold them to purchaſe Trade, and let any man look upon the examples of former times, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the times of <hi>Edward</hi> the II. and ſome others; no one thing gave a deeper and more general diſcontent than the filling of the Kingdom with Aliens, what the inconveniences of ſuch a general diſtaſte would be, is not difficult to judge.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, What if Wars ſhould ariſe between this Kingdom, and thoſe Kingdoms from which the great reſort of Aliens ſhould come, can any man reaſonably think that they would not have reſpect to their Native Countries, where poſſibly many of their Relations, and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, and a great part at leaſt of their Wealth ſhould lodge, or can we think they ſhould wholly be diſmiſt of their Allegiance and Subjection to their Native Princes and Governors, if not, then we have ſo many Enemies Incorporated to us, who may quickly joyn with Native Countrymen, and ruin our Peace and Kingdom, betray all our Counſels, or at leaſt keep us in that awe and fear, that we muſt not break with thoſe Countries upon any Terms, but keep a ſervile and baſe Peace with them upon their own Terms, or engage, in a War with them to our extreameſt danger and diſadvantage. Neither will the Objection of the Parity of our Condition any way help us, for as the Advantage of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Country, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of Trade here, would moſt certainly draw over many
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38110:5"/>Aliens hither, eſpecially out of the populous places of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> ſo the inconveniences of their Countries in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of ours, would ſend but few <hi>Engliſh</hi> among them, in compariſon of their numbers here; ſo we ſhould pour in by this means <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> to the ſtreightning and undoing of the Native <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but without reciprocal disburdening of ours there, till ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity or the want of room or trade in <hi>England,</hi> force the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to that miſerable exchange.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. It is but a fond dream to think that at leaſt the firſt generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of naturalized Aliens would thereupon transfer all their Eſtates hither, there are infinite reaſons why they ſhould not. <hi>Firſt,</hi> War may ariſe between this Kingdom and the Country from whence they came, and the jealouſie of that will make them ſecure, at leaſt, the moſt conſiderable parts of their Eſtates in their own Countries. 2dly. In all probability they will have ſome eſtates which muſt abide there: Debts due to them, and not gotten in, Houſes, Poſſeſſions. 3dly. At leaſt, they will have many of their Relations, as their Fathers, Mothers, Children, Brothers, Kindred which will ſtill keep them upon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon that Countrey, notwithſtanding their Tranſportation. 4thly. Again, here they will find Animoſities and Heart-burnings by the Native <hi>Engliſh</hi> againſt them; upon all which accounts and many more, we may be well aſſured that moſt of them will not venture all in one bottom, but will keep a conſiderable part of their Eſtates and Trade and Relations in the Countries from whence they came: and he is blind that ſees not what the conſequence of that will be, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they will drain the wealth of <hi>England</hi> into their own Hands and Purſes, which they will eaſily tranſmit to their own Countries; that they will make our Countrey the Inſtrument to enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their own Countrey without enriching us; that they will trade from hence into their own Country and Plantations upon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, eaſier, and ſafer Terms then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhall, whereby they will be able to underſel and undermine the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Traders, who ſhall thereby be undone, and not know who hurt them. 5thly. We are miſtaken if we think that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> will be better inſtructed by them, it is true, if a few come over, neceſſity will put them upon employing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> under them, as is done in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and ſome other places at this day; but if many come over they will keep the Trade and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture among themſelves, for tho' ſome of us <hi>Engliſh</hi> have ſo little judgment and good nature as to deliver over our own Country to Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38110:5"/>yet when they come hither we ſhall find them more diſcreet, politick, and better natured to their Countrymen</p>
            <p n="6">6thly. Neither will our Manufactures be better but worſe. We have Laws that Traders in ſome things muſt have ſerved their Apprentice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; but if Aliens come over, muſt they be bound Apprentice before they trade? If ſo, we ſhall have but few of the Artificers come unto us: But if not? Then any Alien may work at any Trade without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, the Law for Apprentices muſt be repealed as to them, and they may work as they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And of the ſame Conſideration will be the priviledges of our great <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cities, <hi>London, York, Briſtol, &amp;c.</hi> Where none but a Freeman may by Cuſtom exerciſe their Trades. Shall all theſe priviledges be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed as to Aliens? If ſo, the Aliens are put into better Condition than the reſt of <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> that are not free of the Cities; and beſides, it is very obvious to ſee what Combuſtions may follow, upon ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions of Liberties of great Cities: but if they ſhall not exerciſe their manual Trades, there the Aliens are diſappointed of what they moſt expected: Namely, trading in theſe places where the greateſt benefit is to be expected; and will not thank us for our Indulgence. And tho theſe two laſt Articles concern Manufactures, and not foreign Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, yet the Conſequence and Extent thereof is large, the Arifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Kingdom are a numerous Company, and thoſe none of the wealthieſt, they will ſooneſt be pinched by this Deſign, and will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain loudeſt. It is true the foreign Artificers are many, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more dextrous in their Manufactures, and poſſibly as well as the Merchants more frugal in their Expences than ours are, or (it may be) are like to be; but all the Conſequence thereof, that is probable to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, is that they will beat the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of Trade and Cuſtom, being able to underſel and underwork them, which will have this effect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that the Manufacture of <hi>England</hi> will be advanced, becauſe delivered ever to Aliens, but the Manufacture of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd, and they at length neceſſitated to become the Journey men and Servants, the Hewers of Wood and Drawers of Water to Strangers that have beaten them out of their Trade, and eaten them out of their Country; and we muſt remember theſe Artificers are a numerous indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent querulous Company of People, and if oppreſſed by Aliens may be troubleſom, diſcontented, and unquiet. We ſee with how much difficulty they are reſtrained from diſorder upon ſmaller Occaſions, even in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to thoſe few forreign Artificers that ſettle among us, what will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38110:6"/>then become of things when every ſecond Houſe ſhall be inhabited and Handy-crafts exerciſed by Foreigners in many Places? And this the Wiſdom of Parliaments have wiſely foreſeen, and therefore have not only inhibited the importation of foreign Manufactures, but alſo tho they incouraged in ſome kind the foreign Merchant, yet have alwayes diſcountenanced, as much as might reaſonably be, the unlimited bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs acceſs of foreign Artificers, farther than might be neceſſary in ſome particular caſes, and places, and purpoſes, and members. To bring over a competent number to teach the Engliſh, but not a deluge to overflow and deſtroy the Engliſh Artificers, as will appear by the Acts of Parliament, and practice of other times.</p>
            <p n="7">7. As large as the Naturalization is propounded to be, ſo large muſt the Tolleration of the exerciſe of Religion be. If the Naturalization be univerſal to all people, as Jews, Turks, Moors, Pagans, as well as Chriſtians, of all ſorts of all Profeſſions and Perſwaſions, ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly muſt be the Extent of the Liberties for the exerciſe of their Religion. The Jews muſt have their Ceremonies, Circumciſions, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues. Turks muſt have their <hi>Mahomitan</hi> Service, and ſo muſt the Moors, and alſo Socinians, Papiſts, Lutherans, and others. For ſince the foundation of the propoſal is the politick conſideration of the increaſe of Trade, and the ſuppoſition is that the more univerſal the Confluence of foreign Traders is, the greater will be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Trade, and the more ample and extenſive the incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, the greater will be the confluence. Of neceſſity, upon theſe ſuppoſitions, the unlimited Tolleration of all Religions will neceſſarily follow; for it will be ridiculous to think, that thoſe People (who are perchance more zealous in their falſe perſwaſions and Religions, than many of us <hi>Engliſh</hi> are of the true Religion) ſhould think themſelves much gratified with a civil priviledge in point of Trade, Commerce, Commorance, and participation of civil Immunities, and yet be fetter'd from the free Practice and Exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; unleſs we pleaſe our ſelves with that baſe Hope, that poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by this means the ſenſe of Religion will become a matter of Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency, and ſtrike ſail to profit, or at leaſt with that unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hope, that true Religion will be more likely to rectifie thoſe falſe Religions, rather than to be corrupted by them.</p>
            <p>And if as an Expedient it ſhall be propoſed that the Tolleration ſhall not be univerſal, but only of the Chriſtian Religion, (tho' there be much to he ſaid againſt the univerſality of ſuch a Tolleration)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38110:6"/>yet let ſuch propoſers conſider, Firſt. That they will not thereby anſwer the latitude and extent of their deſign, for the advantage of Trade to its full Extent; ſince a great part of the trading Men of the World, are Jews, Turks, and Infidels. Again, what <hi>Criterium</hi> ſhall be uſed that may be practicable for the diſcovery of ſuch, and diſcriminating them from others of the Chriſtian Profeſſion. They may come in and plant them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves here in conſiderable Numbers, and keep their Religions cloſe to themſelves 'till their Number ſwell to ſuch a proportion, as may defend them in the open profeſſion and practiſe of that, which at firſt they more modeſtly and politickly concealed till their Numbers, and Wealth, and Intereſt, give them Safety and Impunity in a more free and open profeſſion; ſo that by this means, in a little time, Men of all Nations will be mingled with our Parliaments, and Counſels, and publick Employments, to the hazard of the Ruin and Extirpation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Policy, and Government: and Men of all Religions will be mingled with our Parliaments, Councels, and publick Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to the hazard and deſtruction not only of the Proteſtants, but of the Chriſtian Religion it ſelf; or elſe to the corrupting it to a kind of mungril Religion, like that of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> after their Captivity, they feared the Lord, and ſerved their Idols.</p>
            <p n="8">8thly. This very pouring in of Forreigners into this Kingdom, will endanger the diſſolution, or at leaſt a conſiderable Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the municipal Laws of the Kingdom, and this hath been the experience of this and all other Kingdoms, which have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conſiderable Inroads of other Nations, either with or againſt their Wills, the Inroads of the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> into this Kingdom ſoon brought either Diverſities or Alterations of Laws, and the Reaſons thereof are evident conſiderable Numbers of Foregn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers tranſplanted into another Kingdom, bring along with them the Acquaintance and Knowledge and Love of their own Laws and Cuſtoms; which doth ordinarily occaſion, Firſt, Diverſities of Laws, for when they come in conſiderable Companies, they many times plant themſelves together, and there mantain a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Government and Law among themſelves, which in time prevails and proſpers into a Particular Law for that Society and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38110:7"/>Tract wherein they plant themſelves; and ſo breaks the Unity of the Law, and in time of the Government of a Kingdom. Their Solemnities of Contracts, their Obligations and Rules of Commerce, their Rules of Succeſſions become different, which in proceſs of Time, rankles into the adjoyning Parts and Counties. 2dly, Diſſolution, and alteration, and inſtability in Laws, for in time theſe Foreigners having ſeated themſelves, and grown rich, and potent, will neceſſarily mingle with our Councils, yea, and with our Parliament, and ferment and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milate our Laws to their own; and it will be, and alway hath been found, that diverſity of Laws, and too much lubricity, inſtability, and change of Laws are the cauſes of confuſion and inſtability in Government.</p>
            <p>Now perchance againſt theſe dangers and inconveniences, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in relation to the corrupting of Religion and municipal Laws, theſe, or ſuch as theſe expedients or objections may be projected or imagined.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That the true Religion is ſo reaſonable and effectual, that it may rather reform the falſe Religions than be corrupted by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. That this Tolleration of other Religions here may induce the permiſſion, tolleration, and favour, of the true Religion in other Countries where it is interdicted, and thereby a greater advance of the True Religion may enſue in Foreign Countries, and more than recompence the detriment that true Religion may ſuffer by the entertainment of falſe Religions.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. That there may be ſuch modifications of the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to Foreigners, as may ſecure it againſt innovations either in Religion, Laws, or Government, as may be feared from an imprudent, unlimited, unqualified admiſſion, perchance the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy might be a fitting Expedient, or an excluſion of them from Publick Offices, or diſtributing them into ſeveral quarters, might be a ſufficient corrective for this Fear.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:38110:7"/>
               <head>I ANSWER.</head>
               <p n="1">I. To the firſt of theſe, it is true, that the true Proteſtant Religion hath a great advantage of evidence and worth above other Religions, and it hath by the Bleſſing of God, much prevailed in the World; but we muſt remember our Saviour's anſwer to the Devil's temptation of throwing himſelf down from the Pinacle of the Temple, <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> God Almighty hath given the Children of Men Reaſon and Prudence, and it is to be employed as well in Matters relating to Religion, as in civil Concerns. It were a wildneſs to expect that the corrupt Religions ſhould not more probably infect our weak and corrupted Nature, rather than to think that a true Religion would not receive Corruption by the mixtures of Perſons of corrupt Principles, we ſee at this time, Idolatry, Turciſm, and Popery hath prevailed in ſix parts of ſeven at leaſt, in the habitable World.</p>
               <p n="2">II. To the ſecond, I anſwer, Firſt, How do we know that other Princes will grant a reciprocal Indulgence unto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion? 2. If they will, that they will obſerve and keep it? It will take up a conſiderable time to be ſure of both theſe, and till we are ſure thereof, we are not in any tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition to make or receive this Propoſition. 3. But if we had ſufficient aſſurance, they would make and keep ſuch a reciprocal compact, yet the diſadvantage will ſtill be on our parts. We ſhall never have the advantage to invite the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> into the Foreign Parts of <hi>Europe</hi> or <hi>Aſia,</hi> as they will have to invite them hither; <hi>England</hi> is a fine ſpot of Ground, a rich and convenient Paſture, handſomely encloſed by Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Encloſures, and by civil againſt the Incurſion of Aliens; namely, the Sea and our Laws, and if this incloſure were to be thrown open, that our Neighbours ſhould become inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoners with us upon the ſuppoſed advantage of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ours with them, where one <hi>Engliſhman</hi> would tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant himſelf into <hi>France,</hi> a thouſand Foreigners would tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38110:8"/>themſelves hither, and ſtarve the <hi>Engliſh</hi> into a neceſſity of an unwilling tranſportation of our ſelves into our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour common, and how long, or how well they would be entertained there, we might perchance hereafter know to our loſs; but be it never ſo well, we well know it would be to our loſs.</p>
               <p n="3">III. As to the third, I ſay, we have no neceſſity, thanks be to God, of trying this Experiment: were the Trade of <hi>England</hi> as well managed as it might be without this Experiment, we ſhould have no need of ſearching after ſuch projects to advance it, and therefore it is extream folly to make unneceſſary and hazardous Experiments, in hope to cure them by Expedients, which we are not ſure will be either effectual or ſufficient for it. If the Sea hath broken down the Banks, it becomes us to uſe the beſt means we can by new Ditches and Proviſions to ſtop its progreſs, and ſince we cannot wholly prevent the danger and avoid the loſs, yet to uſe the beſt and likelieſt means we may to render it as eaſie, and as remediable as may be. But it is a madneſs to break down the Banks, and let in the Deluge upon hopes of Expedients, to render it leſs incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and to run ſo great a danger upon proſpect of petty notional imaginations that might as well think to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it. The Safety of States and Kingdoms is of too great a moment without inevitable neceſſity to practice experiments of ſuch a nature. And the Experiment it ſelf in propoſal, is of ſuch a kind, as is not eaſily governable; but will be too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly for the magement and diſpoſal in point of practice, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Men may think in Notions and Speculations: And when all is done, as it may probably do very much harm, ſo it doth not appear to any conſiderate man (that is not fond of his own or others fancies or novelties) that it can bring any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent benefit.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole matter it ſeems, that the Propoſal is to be rejected as dangerous and hurtful to the Kingdom, to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to the Intereſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, as utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evident to produce any conſiderable good to the Kingdom, any way proportionable to the damage and danger thereof; that this excellent boundary and rampire, that the Laws of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38110:8"/>Kingdom have ſettled, and at all times have tenaciouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved againſt the Inundations of Foreigners, ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved as the great Security of the Safety, Priviledge, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Natives; and altho' <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc</hi> upon emergent reaſons, and perſonal merit and aſſurance of ſome particular perſons, acts of Naturalization have been granted; tho' very ſparingly, and cautiouſly, and not by the ſholes (as hath been too much done of late Times) yet there is neither Wiſdom, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, nor fidelity to the King or Kingdom, to go about to throw open this Encloſure, either by an univerſal Naturalization of all, or by any general or national Naturalization of any Foreign Countries or People.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
